So please get your laptop, please get your notepads,
please get your laptops, please get your computers, please get
your tablets, please get your pens and paper.
So it's a nice major.
We are trying to make virtual signaling easier on them.
That's where we had helps a lot.
But it wasn't there.
It was more like an ARCO.
It wasn't really that small of a balloon.
But we got it bigger.
And the thing is everything on Panasonic is square.
So we were finally able to do it.
But it took us like two weeks to get it up to here.
All right, folks.
Let's get started.
Our bookkeeping before we begin lecture.
As posted. So solutions for homeworks one and two are posted on Canvas.
Go ahead and check them out. See how you did.
Grading is on the way.
For homework one, we're almost done. For homework two, we'll get there probably this week.
PA3 and homework three are both posted to Canvas. You should have access.
Homework three is primarily JavaScript.
And it will be covered in the end of today's lecture and Wednesday's lecture.
PA3 is entirely JavaScript as well.
So over the course of the next two weeks, we're currently talking about lambda calculus.
We're going to transition back to JavaScript for a little bit.
And then we're going to power through to Haskell next week.
We're going to be covering three pretty different languages in two weeks.
If that feels confusing and hard, stop by office hours.
In particular, Monday is generally light because the homework was just released.
So if you want to chat about not just homework, come to my office hours after class today.
Some general advice.
There are a lot of people posting, my PA tests are failing on Gradescope.
But they pass all of the local tests. What am I doing wrong?
It's not everyone. I recognize that.
But in general, the tests that I give you locally are not a complete test set.
It's an idea to make sure you've written some idea of the correct function.
The goal of Gradescope is to be the exam test.
So you shouldn't be writing your code, submitting to Gradescope, iterating 500 times.
It's more of write code so that it's probably done.
Submit once. You need to fix one or two things.
Write some more local test cases yourself to try and identify the problem.
Then resubmit.
So that's my advice there.
Write local tests. Local tests, local tests, local tests.
I don't give you everything. I just give you most things.
Okay. Any questions for me?
Anything that we should cover before we start class?
Okay.
Then hopefully today's the last lecture on LambdaCalc for a little while.
So maybe that's good and you like that.
Maybe that's bad because you've been loving it.
Either way, we'll be wrapping it up.
Starting off, we're going to talk about free variables again.
We have three equations that we built out last time.
I'd like for you guys to give me these two equations.
What is the free variables of a complex expression LambdaX.E?
What are the free variables?
Who can tell me?
Yeah.
Yeah. They are the free variables of E minus X.
We have bound X as one of the non-free variables.
It's one of the bound variables.
And then the free variables of a function application E1, E2 are what?
Yeah.
It's the union of what?
Yeah. Definitely.
So we find out whatever the free variables of E1 are.
And then union that with whatever the free variables of E2 are.
This is one set of equations that we care about in LambdaCalc.
What are the free variables of our space?
We did have a question on Wednesday saying,
isn't it all of the variables?
All variables ever?
Not necessarily just the free variables of E.
And to that, I would say a variable is only a variable if it's being used.
So just for that point.
Okay.
This is our second set of equations.
So our first set of equations, these ones to calculate the free variables.
Our second set of equations are about how do we actually do substitution?
How do we do capture avoiding substitution?
And what do we do with these?
What is X where X is E?
How do we reduce the first statement?
Who's got an answer?
Yeah. Go for it.
Just reduces to E.
We get to do our replacement as you would expect.
If X is the value 3, when we see X, we replace it with the value 3.
For example.
All right.
Then we have the variable Y where X is equal to E.
What's this reduced to?
Who's got an answer?
Yeah.
Y if Y is not equal to X.
So assuming these are two different variables, then we just get to ignore whatever we set X to be.
Okay.
What about E1, E2?
Also known as a function application.
E1, E2 where X is equal to E.
How does this reduce?
Yeah.
So we get to say all occurrences of X are replaced with E.
But a little bit more generically, we say all occurrences of X in E1, we will replace with E.
Or we'll continue to recursively substitute inside of E1, X is equal to E.
And we will recursively substitute in E2, X is equal to E.
All right.
And then we have our function, our lambda abstraction.
Lambda X.E1 where X is equal to E.
What do we do here?
Yeah.
Just E1.
Who agrees?
So just E1.
This is, I think, a common point of confusion.
If I can find my pen.
There's a meaningful difference here between lambda X.E1 with the state X is equal to E.
And lambda X.E1 applied to E.
This is an application, a function application, where this is an expression and this is an expression.
This is the parameter to this function.
Here what I'm saying is I have an expression.
And I have some state that goes along with that expression.
Where I can say X is equal to E inside of this expression here.
So these are two different things that we're talking about.
I'm looking up here.
What do we do?
You already got one.
Yeah.
E1 where X is evaluated to E.
E1 where X is equal to E.
What we've done here is we've lost this lambda.
We aren't doing a function application in this expression here.
There's no function application.
So we should end up with a function at the end.
We don't want to substitute in any value into this function.
Because that's not what we're doing at this point.
This here is what we would get if we had said, if I had kept the original thing.
I don't know why I erased it.
If we kept lambda X.E1, E, this would simplify to E1 where X is equal to E.
This is our function application.
E is a parameter to this function.
So X is equal to E. And we get E1 where X is equal to E.
Up here, we have an expression.
And we have state that's going along with it.
Yeah.
Right.
So when we are doing this step here, what we get to do is we get to actually drop our state entirely,
like you've said, and get just lambda X.E1 out of it.
Yeah, question.
That's precisely correct.
So this X is from an outer statement.
It's a different X than this X.
So one way that I personally look at this here, when I see that, I go backwards.
And I say, how did we get here?
We got here by having a lambda X.E.
This is our inner expression.
This corresponds to this piece.
E1, sorry.
And then we had an X, or that's an E.
An E as a parameter to this outer function where we have X as our parameter name.
So we can go backwards from this starting point to get to what it might have looked like before.
Maybe it looked like this.
Maybe it was more complicated.
But if we simplify this line here, we would get to this point.
OK.
Other questions on this one?
Because it definitely can be confusing.
Yeah.
So it can't be E1 and then E. What do you mean by that?
Right.
So why we can't say that this piece here becomes E1 where X is equal to E, or something of this sort, is because this isn't an application.
We aren't making a function call here.
We have an expression, and we have state that goes along with it.
Any time you see square brackets in lambda calculus, we're talking about the state of our kind of world, of our program.
Parentheses and all of this side, that's all the expression.
That's the math that we're actually trying to solve.
This is the accompanying state.
It's not part of the expression.
It's not something that we're going to ever substitute in.
It's just saying this variable is equal to that.
This variable is equal to that.
Yeah.
So basically, that's a bound variable, right?
X.
So wouldn't it be more comfortable for reading?
We could, but we don't need to.
Yeah.
Yeah, so we could kind of accumulate as much state as we want.
We could say X is equal to E, and then we'll replace this one with a Z so that eventually,
we never rewrite this X.
We never overwrite it.
We could do that, but we don't need to.
Yeah.
So this next problem is basically the same sort of similar to this problem?
Yes.
So now, let's move on to this next one.
Lambda Y dot E1, where X is equal to E2.
How do we simplify this?
First of all, what happens if Y is equal to X?
Yeah.
Right, if Y is equal to X, then we just use this rule.
And we say, OK, Y is equal to X.
Then we drop this state, and we'll get lambda X dot E1.
So we can assume Y is not equal to X.
Y is a different variable than X.
What do we want to do now?
Yeah, go for it.
Drop the state.
Well, not necessarily.
What if E1 uses X?
So I think let's actually take a second and look at what this would look like in JavaScript.
You can turn this guy around.
If I have a function that returns Y plus X, so there's a function in JavaScript.
It takes in a parameter Y.
It returns Y plus X.
What if I have the state let X equal 3?
What do I do to simplify my function here?
Go for it.
We can apply the state recursively to the expression.
I love that answer for this generic thing.
Yeah, yeah.
So that is exactly how I would phrase it.
I agree.
In this example, what does that look like?
Yeah.
We can replace the X in our function with 3.
So we can simplify our function to be this.
Because we know the value of X, and we're using that variable X.
So I want to argue that this example here is going to be identical to lambda Y dot Y plus X, where X is equal to 3.
Here, what I have is a function that takes a parameter Y.
It returns Y plus X.
And I have some state that is telling me that X is equal to 3.
This expression is equivalent to the JavaScript expression that I just showed you.
So what we want to do is we have lambda Y dot E1, where E1 is Y plus X.
And we have some state that X is equal to E2, where E2 is 3.
Our goal is to get to lambda Y dot Y plus 3.
And the way we do that is, as your classmate said, we recursively apply our substitution of X is equal to E2 inside of E1.
So what that looks like is that we have lambda Y dot E1 with no parentheses, where X is equal to E2.
So long as Y is not equal to X, which we already covered.
And so long as Y is not in the free variables of E2.
That's a confusing line of math code.
And it might take multiple times staring at it to figure it out.
And that's OK.
That's expected.
Questions on it at this point?
Yeah?
Well, because if Y is equal to X, we have a different rule for that, where we say just drop the state entirely.
So we have that part covered somewhere else.
Yeah?
Other questions?
Well, no, because if Y is equal to X, then we have that.
So you would just, it's kind of like a, consider it like a case statement, where you're matching on these patterns.
If it's this, do that.
So maybe you could say this is redundant, because we've previously checked that Y is not equal to X.
That's not too important to us.
Yeah, so why don't we have this same check for this second-to-last expression?
The reason is because we're entirely dropping the state.
So we're never going to accidentally capture by substituting in E2.
E2 is just kind of erased.
Or E, in this case, is just erased.
Yeah?
Ah, no, these are rules.
Yes, yeah, good question.
These are rules, not examples.
This is the entire rule description of how we do substitution in lambda calculus.
If it was or wasn't?
If it was, yeah.
So what if X is equal to, let's say, 3 plus Y?
So now we have a complicated expression for X.
If we perform the substitution without caring about the fact that, well, actually, first,
is this Y free or is it bound?
This is a free Y.
This is a different Y than this Y.
These two are the same Y.
That's a different Y.
This is a free Y.
These are bound.
So if we do our substitution without checking the free variables, then what we would get
is we would get Y plus X, where X is 3 plus Y.
And now when we look at this expression, which of these Y's is free?
None of them.
They're all bound.
Or they're both bound to this Y.
We've lost that free variable.
And you can see this in JavaScript as well.
If we said that X is equal to Y plus 3, this Y here is different than this Y, very clearly.
We would have to have said somewhere else, let Y equal 7 or whatever we want.
But if we tried to do the substitution that we did here and we said that it's instead equal to Y plus 3,
now we've run into that same problem that we saw with lambda calculus.
This Y is the same as this Y, even though it wasn't the same previously.
So that's why we do this check.
If we didn't, we would capture variables around us.
Yeah, question.
Yeah, no, we don't need to because it's being overwritten.
So it's kind of what we can show this example as well with JavaScript,
where we can say, let Y equal 3.
And now we have a function with the parameter name Y goes to Y plus X.
Inside of this function expression, we don't care that Y was previously equal to 3.
We have shadowed that with our parameter name.
So we get to ignore this previous state when we are evaluating this expression.
That's what the second to last one is saying.
Yeah.
Does this make things more clear, seeing it with JavaScript?
Is this a...
OK, I'm seeing a lot of nods.
That's good.
Because I felt like Wednesday's lecture wasn't quite getting there.
So, all right.
At this point, we've covered the basics of LambdaCalc.
That's everything.
We have free variables.
We have substitution.
Great.
Now, what can we do with it?
Why did I spend two and a half lectures talking about all of this?
Well, I guess, so first of all, the kind of specifics,
we have the ability to do alpha renaming.
Beta reduction is what we just defined.
And then we have this last one, eta conversion,
which is definitely the kind of like weird one.
The way I think of it is, once again, with JavaScript,
that if we have a function that takes in a variable X
and it calls f of X,
so if I have a function that looks like this,
why didn't I just use f?
Because all that I did was create a wrapper around my function f
that took one parameter and passed it right into f.
And I could have instead just used f.
These are equivalent.
That's exactly what the eta conversion is saying.
That if we have a function that takes a single parameter
and it has some complicated expression,
but all that's happening is it takes in one parameter
and passes it along to that expression,
we can simplify that to the expression itself.
This is not a huge thing to worry about.
It's minorly convenient in some cases.
So if it doesn't make full sense, that's fine.
I would recommend just trying to play around with it a little bit,
and that'll probably help.
Okay.
We did this example forever ago.
Well, we can...
Yeah, we can look at it again.
So when we did this example before,
what we found was that the A in the A plus 5
went in for the X,
and then we got into this problem
where the A outside that's free was captured by the A inside.
So what should we have done?
What's our first step?
Who knows?
I heard it from someone.
Raise your hand.
Who was it?
Yeah.
We'll do an alpha rename.
Yeah, an alpha rename of what?
Exactly.
We'll do an inner A,
and we'll name it something else.
In this case, I've called it B.
So we just rename that inner A to be a B.
Then we can do our substitution like normal,
and we can pass in A plus 5 for X,
and we can continue to beta substitute with the 7,
and we'll end up with A plus 12.
So that's what we should have done earlier.
Okay.
There's some more for the ones that,
if you want to do them at home, feel free to.
But that covers formal substitution,
which leaves us with the fun part of LambdaCalc,
why we actually talk about it.
Well, one of the reasons that we actually talk about it
is that we can use it to show off language paradigms.
For example, evaluation order.
This is a question for you guys.
What should we reduce first in this expression?
Yeah.
What's that?
The inner term.
A.
Who votes for A?
Who votes for B?
Like, mostly you guys didn't vote.
It was like a lot of left-hand side voted for A.
What's the reason?
Somebody who voted,
what's your reason for making the choice that you made?
Did you want a third choice?
Who wanted a third choice?
Okay, a decent number of people wanted a third choice.
Somebody back up your claim, whether it's A, B, or C.
Why?
Yeah.
Yeah, sure.
So one thing that we can do is we can actually solve it.
If we take the first approach, the inner term,
we pass z in for y.
That reduces to z.
Then we pass that into lambda x dot x,
so that reduces to z.
If we do it the other way,
we'll pass lambda y dot yz into x,
which gives us lambda y dot yz,
which, when we reduce that one, also gives us z.
They gave us the same thing either way.
So does that mean that it doesn't matter?
I'm seeing some nods.
Yeah, I'm with you.
It doesn't matter.
They both reduce to z.
We got the same thing.
This is formally proved that all expressions
will reduce to the same thing
so long as they reduce to the same thing.
More formally, if you reduce to a normal form,
it doesn't matter what order you do your reductions in.
Okay.
So does that mean the reduction order doesn't matter?
Yeah.
All right.
We have a vote for no.
Anybody else vote for no?
Oh, wait.
That was a...
Does it mean the reduction order...
That was a vote for yes, it does matter.
Who else votes for yes, it does matter?
Who votes for no, it doesn't matter?
Okay, we actually have a little bit of split.
I do want you...
I'll give you the answer.
It does matter.
No, it doesn't not matter.
I don't know.
It does matter.
Why?
You have an idea.
Chat with the people next to you.
Try and come up with a program that it does matter for,
where you get a different result
depending on how you evaluate your code.
Chat with the people next to you.
I'll give you like two or three minutes.
I'm sorry to cut you off.
You clearly have the right idea.
I know the one, I just can't remember the exact formula.
It's like the Y combinator.
Yep, that's one.
Yep, we'll cover those in a minute though.
Okay, quieted down a bit.
Does anybody have a good program?
Something they want to try out?
Who's got an idea?
What can we try?
For a program where it matters, what order are we going?
You were pretty chatty 30 seconds ago.
Something like that?
Okay, how does evaluation order matter here?
Ah, so let's, we're going to do proper substitution.
So we will rename anything that we're supposed to rename.
But definitely true that if we aren't doing proper substitution,
we could get different results one way or the other.
Any other ideas?
Yeah.
Yep.
Yeah, so I like where you're starting here.
The theorem there says, if you reduce to a normal form.
So our goal is going to be trying to construct a function
which is not reduced to a normal form.
Not quite sure what you mean by the input-output though.
What's, like, where they're independent?
Won't that do what you're saying?
But this actually is a normal form.
Okay, so I think it's, to be honest,
I wasn't fully expecting anyone to come up with an answer.
But it's because it's kind of mind-boggling
how you could come up with something
that doesn't reduce to a normal form.
So let's chat about a program that does this.
The program is called Omega.
And Omega is defined as an application of two expressions.
You have the left-hand side, lambda x dot xx.
And the right-hand side, lambda x dot xx.
So what would be our first step in reducing this?
Yeah.
Sure, let's do an alpha rename.
So we have lambda x, xx.
What do you want to rename?
I would basically give, I would number them 1, 2, 4.
Ah, 1, 2, 3, 4.
Yes.
Can we do that?
Which x is this bound by?
The first x.
The first.
Also the first one.
So are these two x's the same?
Yes.
So we could rename these, but they have to be called the same thing.
Yeah.
So we could call this one x1, x1, x1.
This one x2, x2, x2.
Sure.
Now what do we want to do?
Beta reduce.
What does beta look like?
Yeah, so x1 is the parameter name where x1 is equal to this whole thing.
So we will get x1, x1.
That's our inner expression.
x1 is equal to lambda x2 dot x2 x2.
How do we simplify this?
Yeah.
Go back to where we started?
We go back to where we started.
Because x1 and x1 become lambda x2 dot x2 x2.
Which we're back to the alpha renaming step again.
Exactly.
So if we replace this x1 with what x1 is, and we replace that x1 with what x1 is, what we end up with is this expression here.
Which if we alpha rename, removing these numbers, is lambda x dot xx applied to lambda x dot xx.
Which is precisely where we started.
So if we simplify this, we end up back at omega.
That means omega has no normal form.
If you can beta reduce it as much as you want, you'll never end up done.
So when we return to this question of does evaluation order matter, what if we had a function that ignores the input?
And this is kind of what you were getting at, I feel like.
Where we can just toss away the input.
Lambda x dot y.
What happens if we have lambda x dot y where the parameter is omega?
What options do we have for reducing this expression here?
What's one option that we have?
Yeah.
We could pass omega in for x and then return the result, which is y.
We know the value.
We're done.
Y is the result.
So we could return y.
What else could we do?
What's a different way of simplifying this problem?
Yeah.
Right.
We could try and reduce omega.
We could take a beta reduction on omega.
What would that look like?
We'll get the same thing.
Reducing omega gives you omega back.
OK, so now we're here.
What could we do?
What options do we have?
The same thing.
Once again, return y by passing omega in for x, and then ignoring x and returning y.
Or we could try and reduce it again, and again, and again, and again.
At each stage, we have a choice to make.
If you're familiar with non-determinism in Turing machines, this might look pretty familiar.
Where it's like we could take that jump, or we could just stay where we are and kind of sit doing nothing with our epsilon.
So, does it matter?
Yes.
Does it not matter?
No.
It does matter.
But it only matters sometimes.
And most of the time, we can say whatever.
Sometimes, in lambda calc, we have to be pretty precise.
So we can come up with a few different strategies.
The first of which is called call by value.
This is JavaScript's and most languages' approach.
Where we have a function application, E1, E2.
What we will do is first reduce the function.
Then reduce the arguments.
Then apply.
So, any time you're doing a function application, you simplify both sides before applying the actual function call.
We can think of this as...
If we have JavaScript goes to X plus 3, whatever.
So, we have some function.
And we're going to call it with 3 plus 4.
We will simplify our function, which we can't do.
There's no simplification to be made.
Then we simplify the arguments.
And we figure out that this is 7.
Then we pass 7 in for X.
We could instead pass the expression 3 plus 4 in for X.
We would get the same thing here.
But that's a different route that we could take.
JavaScript says reduce the arguments.
Then apply.
So, if we...
You know, like, following that, we simplify the red.
Then we simplify the blue.
Then we apply the thing.
So, if we look at this JavaScript function.
X goes to 33 with this parameter as input.
What are we going to get as our result?
You have to turn on your visual debugger.
What do we get?
Who's got an idea?
One person.
Chat with somebody next to you.
Figure out.
What does this give us?
How many of you said this?
Range error maximum call stack exceeded.
Why?
What happened here?
Where did we go wrong?
Yeah?
Exactly.
No, no, no.
So, we're trying to reduce the right-hand side value in blue.
And this is a recursive function.
What is this function?
What's another name for the blue part?
Yeah.
Omega.
That's what we just saw.
In lambda calculus.
That's omega.
In JavaScript.
Yeah, so it's not gonna work.
What if we wanted it to work?
Haskell, which we will start studying soon, takes a different approach.
That's more similar to call by name.
Where what we do is we reduce the function.
And then we apply.
The only thing that's different than call by value is that we aren't reducing the argument.
You don't reduce the argument ever.
You only ever reduce the function.
And what that means is we will only use a value if it's being used.
To go to our example over here, which was bad JavaScript.
If we have a function X goes to 3, and we pass in 3 plus 4, but we aren't using X, why would you evaluate 3 plus 4?
We didn't need that.
Wasted computation.
Ice caps are melting and all that, you know?
This 3 plus 4 is the fault.
So we can just toss it out instead because it's never used.
Never evaluate something if it's not gonna be used.
So this is your first, for some of you, your first time ever seeing Haskell.
But it looks surprisingly similar to lambda calculus.
Where we have lambda X dot 33, lambda X dot XX, lambda X dot XX.
What will this program evaluate to?
If you know nothing about Haskell except for what I've just said up above.
Yeah?
33.
Because we don't use our parameter X, this piece here being omega, we'll never reduce omega.
Which means we'll never try to go into this infinite loop, and we'll end up with the value 33.
Now you guys know Haskell.
That wasn't so hard.
All right.
Questions?
Is there any of this?
Yeah.
No.
That's...
Yeah?
Yeah.
No.
So it'll do the beta reduction to pass this all in for X.
And then it won't need to use X.
So it will never evaluate that state.
So up above what you can see, only the pointer worked.
We evaluate the left-hand side, the red.
Simplify that as much as we can.
And then the beauty of it is that we get to this E1 prime 33, where X is equal to this
omega.
And since we never use X, we can just toss away the state.
And we'll return 33.
Yeah?
What do you mean by sharing?
Oh, yeah, yeah.
So what if...
What if we have a function that takes X and returns X plus X?
Then it's great to precompute 3 plus 4.
Now we're saving the polarized caps.
Because we're doing 7 plus 7 instead of 3 plus 4 plus 3 plus 4.
And if you do 3 plus 4 plus 3 plus 4, you've duplicated your computation.
Which might seem trivial, but I promise you it's not.
This is exactly what compilers are doing all the time to optimize your code.
So what Haskell does is it says, until you need something, don't evaluate it.
As soon as you need it, store it.
So we're gonna compute 3 plus 4 for X.
And then we're just gonna use that same value a second time.
We don't need to recompute it.
So that's what the sharing means.
Yeah?
So, no, that's part of the runtime environment.
But well, to the extent it can do these things at compile time, it will.
But it can't do everything.
Other questions?
Cool.
So in summary, you can have the technical term redexes or some terms that can reduce.
Your evaluation strategy tells you which term to evaluate and reduce.
You aren't guaranteed to find a normal form.
These are two different ways that you could...
Two different strategies to solve lambda expressions.
All right.
That concludes lambda calc.
However, in the slide deck, there are about 15 more slides about more fun things you can
do with lambda calculus, such as creating booleans, creating numbers, creating functions
we've already done, doing tuples, structs, and in particular, recursion, which is not
required for the course and will not be part of standard exam points.
There's some fun slides on it, too.
We talked about the Y Combinator, but not the VC firm.
So I would encourage you, if you have at all enjoyed lambda calc, or if it's just at all
interesting to check it out.
Those last few slides.
But otherwise, we're going to be leaving lambda calc in its place and use it as a way of talking
about some of these other ideas.
So any lingering questions on lambda calc?
Yeah.
So what should you take away from lambda calc?
I think it's a fair question.
First of all, for the exam, but also more broadly speaking, the goal of a lot of the
parts of this class are to improve your visual debugger, as I mentioned as I brought up
earlier.
Where it's not necessarily that you're ever going to write lambda calc.
But you will look at a lot of functions as software engineers.
That's something that you will do.
And being able to spot how they work and what they're doing and how things will evaluate
is very important.
With respect to your grade, you need to be able to evaluate a lambda calc expression.
And say what are the free variables of this expression?
What will it reduce to?
Will it reduce?
Or will it not reduce?
That sort of thing.
Or write a lambda calc expression that does X, Y, Z.
That's the sum of it.
Other last questions?
Otherwise, feel free to bring up any other stuff during office hours as well.
Yeah?
In general, is it easier to start from the expression you go out?
It really depends on the expression.
Yeah.
The fact that JavaScript does it one way and Haskell does it another way is kind of indicative
of there's no right answer.
It's not that one of the two of them is smarter and better.
It's that they're different approaches.
Either one might be better.
Okay.
So what we have been talking about is lambda calculus's substitution model.
Where we said we could have a function with a function application and we can beta reduce
it to some other expression.
In JavaScript, that above function looks something like this.
And why we care about it is because we can do this beta reduction at compile time.
That's not a runtime evaluation.
That's a compile time simplification of your code.
So that at runtime, we don't need to compute it.
And if you're gonna do this over and over, then compile once, run ten times, it's highly
effective to beta reduce.
But why would you not want to do that?
If we tried to do beta reduction on these slides are on Canvas, by the way, already.
So if you do that and follow along, they are already up there.
Why would you not want to do a beta reduction in a real language like JavaScript?
Where we're trying to say set X equal to some parameter for all X in some scope.
What can go wrong?
Yeah.
In JavaScript, we can update the value of X.
X might be something at the start of a function and change to be something else at the end
of the function.
We've been working with JavaScript that looks like this, but that's not actually all of
JavaScript's power.
We could say X equals X plus 1 on the second line of this function.
And then if we've substituted everything, we're kind of, like, in a limbo land.
It can also slow things down.
We don't need to get into that.
But to point out this idea of change and mutation in JavaScript, if we had a relatively simple
function, let Y equal 1, Z equal 0, Z plus plus, log Z, what do we expect to be the output
of console.log?
1.
Right?
We've started Z as 0, we incremented Z, and then we output Z.
If we did a beta reduction of all Z is equal to 0, then when we get to this log, we log
0.
So most languages support this idea of mutation.
Variables are not static.
They change.
They're called variable for a reason.
Pascal has a different idea and says variables aren't variable.
They are static.
And part of the reason for that is so that they can do more substitution.
So what can we do about this?
We're going to spend the next lecture and a half talking about how to translate from
the kind of mathematician ivory tower of lambda calculus, not quite all the way down
to the machine model, but talk about the environment model of JavaScript somewhere in between.
Where we get some of the benefits of lambda calculus, but we aren't all the way in the
nuts and bolts of things.
It'll look like this.
This is what we're going to kind of be covering.
What does scope look like?
How do first order functions yeah.
First order functions to start.
How do those work with scope?
How do free variables play into this?
And then finally, how do high order functions work with scope?
So to start, what is a scope?
What's the point of a scope?
What do you use it for?
You guys have a lot of answers.
Someone who hasn't brought something up.
I do appreciate it, just to be clear.
It's not bad that you guys answer a lot of questions.
What's the point of a scope?
You guys use these all the time.
When was the last time you wrote code?
It's like yesterday.
Right?
There was a PA.
You had to use a scope in the PA.
Yeah?
No, definitely.
So to make variables easier to use, I think, is a pretty concise summary of what's the
point of a scope.
We want to encapsulate and hide these variables live here.
It doesn't care about, like, these variables don't matter anywhere else.
Don't use the same X that I've defined here in some other place.
Yeah?
PA is due next week.
PA2 should be due this Sunday.
Is that not what grade scope says?
I'll fix that.
It should be this Sunday.
PA2 and 3 are due, like, this upcoming Sunday.
Not yesterday.
No.
Oh, yeah.
I guess I did just say...
Yeah, no.
Some of you might have been writing code.
I don't know.
Whatever.
You guys should probably be writing more code than you are currently writing.
That's definitely true.
For probably 99 of you.
But PA is due in six days or something like that.
Yep.
Don't worry if you didn't submit it.
Okay.
So scopes.
The point of them is to encapsulate state specific to the area of code that we're working
on.
Right?
If we're saying X here is equal to this thing, this is where I'm gonna use X with this value.
Not elsewhere in, like, a different library.
I don't want that other implementation of X.
I want my version of X.
So how are we gonna capture that?
We are...
We're not going here.
But we are gonna be somewhere in the middle here, where we're talking about, like, what
do we need to actually use a scope?
If we wanted to track this idea of the environment of our program over time, we're gonna need
some information.
So going to the previous example, we're going to create environments, which I call activation
records of whatever we are currently executing.
When we are inside of one scope, we want information about that scope.
It's doing X in this scope.
And we're going to contain all of our variables in this environment.
And then we're also going to contain some extra information.
If you've taken kind of lower level classes, where you've done Spark or MIPS or X86 or
whatever, you have to keep track of things like the stack pointer, the return address,
the frame pointer.
This is environmental information about what we're currently executing.
So what we might do is, for the current snippet, we could have our environment pointer point
to this area of memory, where we've said Y is equal to 1, Z is equal to 0.
This is our state.
It's our square brackets from lambda calculus.
As opposed to the code, the expressions that we're going to execute.
Depends on the setup.
Okay.
One minor piece of this that we kind of ignore after this one slide.
But there's the canonical idea of R values and L values.
R values are true expressions where we can treat them like lambda calculus.
They're very mathematical.
We can simplify as much as we want.
There's no backing environment to them.
And L values are pointers to R values.
They're like the buckets that you learn about with variables.
So L values point to R value information.
And when we look at something like plus plus, when we say Z plus plus or plus plus Z, we
can't plus plus an R value, because plus plus is mutating the state.
So you can only plus plus an L value so that it can update itself.
So in our thing over here, the left-hand side, the YZ, those are our L values that
are pointing to R values on the right-hand side.
We can plus plus Z. You can't plus plus 0.
Because plus plus 0, it's like, what does that even mean?
Maybe it returns 1.
Maybe it doesn't.
But it certainly doesn't update the number 0 to be 1.
That would be really weird.
If later, you then, like, use 0 and got 1.
Goodness.
OK.
So that's L values, R values, whatever.
When we want to execute console.log Z, we will go look at our environment and say, what
context are we evaluating console.log Z in?
Oh, sorry.
We're looking at the Z plus plus first.
When we execute Z plus plus, we say, what environment are we executing that in?
Our environment is the little square.
We go look up the value of Z. Z is 0.
We increment it to 1.
So we find our environment.
We check to see if we're inside of the environment.
And then we use the environment.
When we log Z, the process is the same.
We find what our current environment is, which is whatever our environment pointer
points to.
We look up the value of Z. What's the value of Z?
What's the value of Z?
1.
Yeah.
It's in the table right there.
So we print out 1.
This algorithm sounds a little slow.
That's because it is.
It's not very convenient to continually look up the environment pointer, check what my
variables are.
Is my variable there?
If it's not, go find it somewhere else.
That's partially because we're not in the machine model.
We aren't talking about x86 or Spark.
But it's also just a kind of necessary evil.
You have to be able to find what is my environment.
So we can come up with kind of, like, speedy hacks around it.
But at the end of the day, we have to do this approach.
Anytime we're executing code, we have to know what environment are we executing that code
in.
Because it's very different to log Z here than in a totally different program where
you said Z is 100.
Or Z is omega.
Or, you know, whatever.
Those mean different things depending on the environment.
OK.
That's the anatomy of a scope.
Which is not, like, it's not crazy.
It's not supposed to be something totally new.
Scopes are scopes.
Scopes store variables.
Right?
When do we create environments?
When do we create scopes?
Chat with someone next to you.
When do we need to do these?
A, B, A and B, or never?
How many people vote A?
Every time we create a new block scope.
Or every time we enter a new block scope.
How many people vote B?
Every time we enter a new function scope.
How many people vote A and B?
All right.
We got a majority there.
Anybody say we don't need new environments?
OK.
Nobody's really...
Oh, maybe we have a jokester.
There are some worlds where you might have a language that doesn't create new environments.
It's not unreasonable.
And there was a version of JavaScript where you didn't have new block scopes.
Or new scope on a block scope.
Because we only really cared about function scope.
Nowadays, it's A and B. Whenever you create a new block scope or a new function scope.
Then we create a new environment.
So the approach we're gonna take, and we're gonna spend a lot of time drawing these diagrams,
and this is basically what the homework looks like, is we will have a function.
We will call that function.
And then we're going to keep track of the environment as we execute that code.
And one of the main points of this chunk of class is so that you can look at this code
and say...
I know what that's gonna do.
Here it's pretty obvious.
It's factorial.
We called it fact.
That's not always the case.
Sometimes you're presented with code that looks like...
What the heck is this doing?
Being able to trace through it and understand what state is looking like as you are tracing
through it is extremely valuable.
It saves you a lot of time.
Rather than having to put a bunch of console.log inside of the code and then run it and run
it.
Or put a breakpoint and run it and run it.
So we're finishing up with class now.
We're gonna pick up on Wednesday diving into how can we track environment as we run JavaScript
code.
Feel free to drop by office hours.
Otherwise, have a good week.
Bye.